[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank D Freitas
and welcome to hellotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to a brand new season season
of holotalk for the 2000-2001 season
this is the fourth season of the show
and I would like to welcome all of the
regular listeners back and also welcome
the new listeners who had gotten on the
email list over the summer anticipating
a new season of shows so welcome to
holotalk Our Guest this week is Sean
Lolly and Sean is the science department
head at Sewickley Academy in Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania and I in
Sean when I was in Pittsburgh during one
of my trips and got some of his thoughts
on holography and education and working
with kids and he'll come on and tell us
a little bit about his program and a
little bit about holography in the
innesburg area in general and also how
they're going to start using the new
shoebox holography
system there at Dennis Whitley Academy
before I do I'd like to let the
listeners know especially the new
listeners that there is an archive of
holotalk shows that you can access where
all three years of programming is
located for your listening enjoyment if
you scroll down the whole talk page you
will find a link that will take you to
the archive and then you can just scroll
down the archive page and pick out any
show that happens to suit your interest
click on it and you'll be able to listen
to that show
just the way that you're listening to
this one now and once again there are
three years of holotalk programming
there
it's good to be back it wasn't a great
summer weather-wise anyway here in the
Northeast part of the country it was a
very rainy damp chilly
but overall it was good to have a break
each year our regular listeners know and
whole talk goes off the air at Memorial
Day
and then we just stay off the air for
the entire summer and actually
activities around the lab also seem to
settle down somewhat and there are a few
Workshop programs and we did do a few
shows over the summer as well but for
all practical purposes it's basically
just a shutdown for the summer to
recharge and come back with the
anticipation of a brand new season of
both working in the lab Workshop
programs and whole Talk itself
we have a lot of guests coming up this
year and we'll invite you to come back
on log on and listen to some of the
exciting shows that we have coming up
speaking to people who are working with
lasers and holography we're also going
to have a
section for projects like I did with the
laser diode holography back last year
and a little bit of the year before
where you log on and follow the project
itself who should have some pretty cool
projects not just for your amateur and
hobbyists
holographers out there but also for
educators as well
I'd like to take Hollow talk on the road
a little bit more this year most of the
programs that are on the archive page
have been with interviews that have been
conducted over the phone and last year
was one of the first years that I took
holotalk out on the road and did some
interviews with the equipment and I'd
like to continue to do that at different
Labs Studios and events that are held
throughout the season so we can look
forward to that
before we get to Sean Lolly I have a few
announcements General announcements to
make I'd like to announce that the Open
House program is going to start up once
again
for those of you who are not aware of
the open house the the first Wednesday
of each month from Labor Day through
Memorial Day
I open up the studio and allow people to
come in and see some of the Holograms
how Holograms are made and there's
usually a specific topic for each one of
the months sometimes it's laser diet
Holograms sometimes it's hologram
portraits sometimes it's a multi-color
holography etc etc the first open house
that I'm going to have is going to be
October 4th that's Wednesday October 4th
at 7 30 here at the lab in Allentown and
you're welcome to come out have some
refreshments see some Holograms take a
look at how Holograms are done and
generally have a pretty good time so
that's open house the first one of the
Season October 4th 7 30. so if you
happen to be in the New York
Philadelphia Baltimore Washington DC
areas and you get out of work at 4 30 or
5. usually two and a half hours is
enough time to to get up here or over to
here or down to here whichever way you
happen to become coming from to enjoy
the open house and it usually runs about
an hour and a half so you're out of here
at nine o'clock within enough time to
get back to your home in time to get to
bed and back up for another day on
Thursday mornings
new season of Workshop programs are
starting up if you go to the workshop
page you'll see the listing of workshops
there's the introduction to holography
Workshop where you can come in learn how
to make a hologram make one of your own
Holograms from start to finish to take
home with you to One of a Kind hologram
and you also learn a little bit about
making them in the process because
you're doing it Hands-On
if you're an educator and you would like
to start hologography with your students
at your school there's no better way to
do so than to come in here for an
afternoon or evening Workshop we'll take
you through everything that you need to
know to put a successful and exciting
program together for your students to
enjoy holography in the school so
there's a teacher educator program as
well
new this season is speaking engagements
if you if you happen to have a club or
organization I'd be more than happy to
come out and speak about holography
bring a few Holograms with me bring a
laser or two so that you can see how
lasers work
especially the new diode lasers and if
you'd like more information on that you
can find that on the workshop page as
well and if you happen to be in the New
York Philadelphia and I believe
Baltimore area as well let me know this
is something I do as a public service
it's not anything that I charge for so
if you have a club organization you're
having a special education night or you
want an interesting topic with Blazers
and photography contact me either
through email or through the telephone
and I'd be more than happy to come down
if the date happens to be open and speak
at your event
okay let's move on to Sean Lolly from
Sewickley Academy this is the first
interview of the year and I'd like to
thank you for tuning in and I hope that
you tune in each and every week to enjoy
a new whole talk program throughout this
season which will run from tonight
through Memorial Day of 2001. I'm
looking forward to a great season and
it's good to be back here's Sean Lolly
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
welcome to another week of Holo talk
we're on the road in Pittsburgh this
week and I have as a special guest
actually here in the hotel room with me
is uh Sean Lally and Sean is from
Sewickley Academy that's right in
Sewickley Pennsylvania just close to
here
um why don't you take a minute to uh
tell a little bit about the school is it
K-12 or you know a general background
about the academy itself absolutely it's
K-12 actually pre-k through 12 uh
college preparatory school and we are
located in Sewickley Pennsylvania which
is probably about 20 minutes or so from
here and it's a again it's called
Preparatory School
um private school yeah now you've been
working with holography for a number of
years haven't you about almost 12 years
yeah now yeah uh pretty much exclusively
in education yeah and how did you get
started with it uh
pretty much by accident
the uh I had an opportunity a friend of
mine wanted to do some teaching uh one
summer with me at West Virginia
University and they were interested in
having a holography course and nobody in
the physics department had really had
any luck with it yeah so they gave it to
us as a project to play with because we
were the kind of people who like to play
with that sort of thing and um
sure enough we we eventually had some
great success with it this is sort of as
far as I can tell it was before the big
wave of uh of great interest in
holography especially in teaching
physics yeah I do I teach High School
physics and astronomy so that's that is
my background we started it then we had
some great success with it and once
plates and whatnot became much easier to
get a hold of uh I did it every single
year after that
um with uh with my high school kids and
but I've also done with kids as young as
a boy we've done Holograms with kids
like five six seven years old in summer
workshops yeah and you've done Holograms
specifically with your students in your
course now right definitely we do a
regular part of the physics curriculum
and your chair of the science department
okay just so we let the whole talk
listeners know that sure you got
interested in the shoe box where do you
see this falling in place now with the
holography you think it's a lot easier
now without a doubt I haven't uh
I haven't seen anything quite this
simple ever before and when I see the
results of these plates they I mean they
just blow me away I think they're
amazing they are better than some of
they're better than the most of the work
that I've done with uh simple uh healing
me on lasers before I think they're it's
amazingly
um
amazingly uh exciting development and
again as you know I'd always heard that
it just wasn't possible on physics list
serves it always came up as just
something that could not be done and
and dying to do this
if you happen to hear a noise in the
background we have somebody with a weed
whacker that's working out there so
sorry about that and if this turns out
to be too inaudible which I don't think
it's gone I think I think maybe we can
work with it but maybe I can give you a
call on the phone that'd be great or a
phone interview or something no problem
now when you work with your kids and you
go over things like lasers and
holography and stuff like that
do they ever find out anything about
that there's actually careers you know
that they can move into not really you
know that's uh I don't know much of the
current career Market myself so I've
been in education for 12 years
um
I've had Engineers come in to speak to
them but I think that something like a
photonics probably seems a bit bit so
specialized that I know I never really
realized that there was such a great
need in the market right now for uh for
trained people did you know that one of
the largest photonics corridors in the
nation is just going to be a few miles
from here that I did know okay yeah I
did know that but I had no idea that we
were talking about a great demand for uh
for trained people yeah do you think it
would be something would be valuable for
kids to know about sure what grades do
you teach I teach uh 11 and 12. also I
guess that would probably be right
around the age when they would start to
make careers on what I mean decisions on
what type of careers they would make
without a doubt um in the Summers I
teach younger kids like um you know
fourth grade fifth grade and that's when
I've done some a lot of food workshops
with them as well set up they're like
yourself just go at the drop of a hat
anywhere I can get a dark room get set
it up and uh and do a setting do a bunch
of exposures with kids
what percentage of kids go on to a
four-year degree program that come out
of sequel I imagine it's a fairly high
percentage Yeah I'd say it's almost 100
if not 100 yeah definitely it's I mean
that's why they're there to to get into
uh ideally the school of their choice
yeah it's a pretty it's a really
rigorous program but it's also a fairly
it's very um
very academic but it is also
a highly concentrated in the Arts and
Humanities as well so there's an
incredible music program and uh you know
a really wonderful art program as well
it's great I like working there because
all the people that I work with practice
for the most part what they do so you
know people in my science department
have most of them have some kind of
science research background yeah the art
program they're artists you know a music
programmer professional musician who's
great via the English program they're
all writers it's a cool place to work
yeah it is yeah
um and they support my uh my activities
and things like uh with holography or
astronomy if I have I mean when I look
to hire somebody I always look for
somebody who has great outside interests
so that you know we can we can really
tap that yeah what about holography
generally in the Pittsburgh area has
there been a lot of activity over the
years a few people a lot of people um
there I would say there has been a lot
of activity from a few people the uh the
two names that always come to and when I
think of holography or Dan and Kathy
Malone Dan teaches at Fox Chapel high
school he's a public school in Fox
Chapel and uh Kathy Side Academy which
is another College Prep School in both
great schools and I've learned an awful
lot about holography from them I think
they probably started doing it in the
early 90s and they started offering
workshops around here for holography and
they trained a lot of people to how to
do uh how to do simple Holograms
although it's not nearly as simple as
the shoebox technique without a doubt
but they have done a lot of great things
for holography education in this area
and not just in this area I know they've
done National workshops Regional
workshops as well they're incredibly
dedicated and uh and
um and
involved physics and Educators do you
have any holographic artists that
continue with doing holography here
after they've taken one of the workshops
oh teachers yes teachers yes we've had
people do you have anyone that like Sam
Jones down on 28th street does he have a
lab in his basement or something uh none
that I've known him but I've had a lot
of students not a good bit with it in
our school yeah so that's one of the
nicest things that holography has
afforded and that's the opportunity to
do great research projects we have a
thing in Pennsylvania called you
probably know the Pennsylvania Junior
Academy of Science
they do legitimate scientific research
and they present it to their peers as
well as College professors High School
teachers engineers and it's a
competition but it's more of a an
exhibition so I've had students do
research projects on pseudo-color
holography with color with chemical
preparation of plates when uh 360 degree
holography with flexible film yeah
multi-image Holograms there's all sorts
of things and they've all almost always
a preparation of uh of documented
Shelton's what we tried this year with
pretty mixed results yeah but all the
projects always uh do very well because
they are interesting in their original
projects and they're not just something
as sort of mundane as you know which
battery lasts the longest yeah yeah yeah
the great project and we're not talking
about something that's really cost
prohibitive for schools that's why I
liked it before I taught it Sewickley
Academy I taught at a uh Aurora Public
School and the budget there was terrible
you know you know it just wasn't good at
all but we could still do great work in
holography I had a I got a grant from
the local spectroscopy Society of
Pittsburgh to uh to buy a laser the next
thing I know and some plates
and that that lasted a long time and uh
we've got an awful lot out of that so
it's I've never found especially now I
mean a lot of he's not a cost
prohibitive uh Endeavor and there's so
much physics oh yeah that the kids learn
from this process and they love it it's
interesting
and it's a quiet lab yes it's a nice
quiet it's a quiet lab you get the kids
to be quiet for a while I know exactly
well I want to thank you very much for
coming on the show Absolutely and I hope
that we have an opportunity to move
forward and work together maybe on a few
projects I know you found the portraits
fascinating incredibly exciting
um yeah I would uh welcome the
opportunity to work with you and also
any other Educators yeah okay sure well
thank you very much thanks a lot